Ryan A. Venturelli [she/her]

CONTACT Information

College of Marine Science Phone: (219) 808-0251
University of South Florida F-mail: rayenturelli@n

University of South Florida E-mail: raventurelli@mail.usf.edu
St. Petersburg, FL 33701 USA Website: www.rad-subglacial.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

Isotope geochemist with expertise in geochronology, subglacial carbon cycling, and clumped isotope paleothermometry. I take a process-to-paleo approach using sub-ice (subglacial and grounding-line-proximal) sediments to reconstruct Antarctic Ice Sheet change since the Last Glacial Maximum.

EDUCATION

University of South Florida, St. Petersburg, Florida USA

PhD in Marine Science, expected graduation: December 2020

Dissertation: Unravelling Paleoclimate's Gordian Knots: Assessing The 'What?' and 'When?' of Holocene Climate Change from Antarctica to the Florida Keys

Advisor: Dr. Brad E. Rosenheim

Indiana State University, Terre Haute, Indiana USA

Master of Science in Earth and Quaternary Systems, 2015

Thesis: The Ecology of Deep Sea Benthic Foraminifera on the California Margin: Epifaunal

Taxa in an Infaunal World

Advisor: Dr. Anthony E. Rathburn

Indiana University Northwest, Gary, Indiana USA

Bachelor of Science in Geology, 2013

Undergraduate Research: Late Holocene dune development and shift in dune-building winds along southern Lake Michigan

Advisor: Dr. Zoran Kilibarda

REFEREED
JOURNAL
PUBLICATIONS

- [5] Venturelli, R. A., Siegfried, M.R., Roush, K.A., Li, W., Burnett, J. Zook, R., Fricker, H.A., Priscu, J.C. Leventer, A., and Rosenheim, B. E. (in press). Mid-Holocene Grounding Line Retreat and Re-advance at Whillans Ice Stream, West Antarctica. Geophysical Research Letters.
- [4] **Venturelli, R. A.**, and Rosenheim, B. E. (2019). Compositional and beam-size-dependent effects on pressure baseline in clumped isotope mass spectrometry. *Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry*, 33(1), 140-148.
- [3] Petersen, S.V., Defliese, W.F., Saenger, C., Daëron, M., Huntington, K.W., John, C.M., Kelson, J.R., Bernasconi, S.M., Colman, A.S., Kluge, T., Olack, G.A., Schauer, A. J., Bajnai, D., Bonifacie, M., Breitenbach, S.F.M., Fiebig, J., Fernandez, A.B., Henkes, G.A., Hodell, D., Katz, A., Kele, S., Lohmann, K.C., Passey, B.H., Peral, M.Y., Petrizzo, D.A., Rosenheim, B.E., Tripati, A., Venturelli, R.A., Young, E.D., and Winkelstern, I.Z. (2019). Effects of improved ¹⁷O correction on interlaboratory agreement in clumped isotope calibrations, estimates of mineral-specific offsets, and temperature dependence of acid digestion fractionation. Geochemistry, Geophysics, Geosystems, 20(7), 3495-3519.
- [2] Venturelli, R. A., Rathburn, A. E., Burkett, A. M., and Ziebis, W. (2018). Epifaunal foraminifera in an infaunal world: insights into the influence of heterogeneity on the benthic ecology of oxygen-poor, deep-sea habitats. *Frontiers in Marine Science*, 5, 344.
- [1] Kilibarda, Z., **Venturelli, R.A.**, and Goble, R. (2014). Late Holocene dune development and shift in dune-building winds along southern Lake Michigan. *Coastline and Dune Evolution along the Great Lakes. Geological Society of America Special Paper*, 508, 47-64.

RESEARCH FUNDING
FELLOWSHIPS AND AWARDS

University of South Florida

Von Rosenstiel Innovation Award, 2019

\$5,000

Project: Isotopic and Carbonate Chemistry Characteristics of an Antarctic Subglacial Lake

National Ocean Science Accelerator Mass Spectrometry Laboratory

Graduate Student Internship, 2019

\$10,213*

Project: Investigating Carbon Cycling in an Actively Draining Antarctic Subglacial Lake

*analytical cost covered by program

Geological Society of America

Graduate Student Research Grant, 2018

\$2,000

Project: Deconvolving Holocene Hydrologic Variability Along the Florida Keys Reef Tract

S

University of South Florida

College of Marine Science

Gulf Oceanographic Trust Fellowship, 2018-2019 \$12,000 Jack and Katharine Ann Lake Fellowship, 2017-2018 \$13,000 Paul Getting Endowed Memorial Fellowship, 2016-2017 \$13,000 Anne and Werner Von Rosenstiel Fellowship, 2015-2016 \$25,000 OFFICE OF GRADUATE STUDIES International Travel Grant, 2017 \$1,519

Graduate Student Research Symposium Presentation Winner, 2017

Indiana State University

College of Graduate and Professional Studies

Research and Creativity Award, 2015 \$500

EARTH AND ENVIRONMENTAL SYSTEMS

\$100 Outstanding Graduate Assistant Award, 2015

Indiana University Northwest

GEOSCIENCES

Karen Brunson Memorial Award, 2013

\$300

\$500

FIELD EXPERIENCE

Subglacial Antarctic Lakes Scientific Access (SALSA) Project

Mercer Ice Stream, West Antarctica

2018-2019

Subglacial water and sediment sampling

McMurdo Station, West Antarctica

2017-2018

Contamination remediation and preparation of a deep field laboratory

Scripps Institution of Oceanography Student Cruises

Chief Scientist: Dave Checkley, R/V Robert Gordon Sproul

2014

Multicore sediment sampling

Chief Scientist: Peter Franks R/V Robert Gordon Sproul

2013

Multicore sediment sampling

Geology Field Camp: Michigan Technological University and University of Cape Town

Western Cape, South Africa

2011

Mapping of Proterozoic to modern geologic structures

Teaching EXPERIENCE

University of South Florida

	Teaching Assistant Courses: Geological Oceanography (2 semesters) Physical Oceanography (1 semester)	2017-2020
	Indiana State University Laboratory Instructor Courses: Introduction to Environmental Science (3 semesters) Earth Science (1 semester) Historical Geology (1 semester)	2014-2015
	Teaching Assistant	2015
	Course: Historical Geology (1 semester) Field Instructor for geologic mapping trip in Western United States Course: Structural Geology (1 semester)	2015
	Michigan Technological University and University of Cape Town Teaching Assistant Course: Geology Field Camp in the Western Cape, South Africa	2013
	Indiana University Northwest Laboratory Instructor	2012-2013
	Course: Introduction to Earth Science (4 semesters)	
	Teaching Assistant Courses: Geomorphology (2 semesters) History of Earth (2 semesters) Principles of Sedimentation and Stratigraphy (2 semesters)	2011-2013
Professional Engagement	Referee Service Journals: Rapid Communications in Mass Spectrometry, Radiocarbon	
	Conference Service AGU Fall Meeting Session Chair: Sub-Ice-Sheet and Sub-Ice-Shelf Environment Bridging the Gap Between Modern Observations and Geologic Records Program Organizing Committee: ComSciCon Local Organizing Committee: 5th International Clumped Isotope Workshop	ents: 2019, 2020 2018, 2019 2016
Public	Presentations	
Engagement	Taste of Science Tampa Bay Event	2019
	Title: Subglacial Lake Science: From Space Lasers to Sediments University of South Florida REU program	2019
	Title: Subglacial Lake Science: From Space Lasers to Sediments Campbell Park Elementary School Title: What do Antarctic Scientists do?	2018
	Demonstrations	2015 2010 2010
	Baypoint Elementary Science Night Glacier Race and Ocean Circulation Tanks	2017, 2018, 2019
	St. Petersburg Science Festival 201 Glacier Race and Ocean Circulation Tanks	15, 2016, 2017, 2018
	National Ocean Sciences Bowl, Spoonbill Bowl Science Judge	2015, 2016
	Organizational Service St. Petersburg Science Festival Program Committee Chair Managed scientific participants for an event that attracts 20-30,000 people pe	2016-2018 er year
Conference Abstracts	[16] Venturelli, R. A., Rosenheim, B.E. Leventer, A., Harwood, D., Patterso	on, M.O., Campbell,

- T., Siegfried, M.R., Fricker, H.A., SALSA Science team, and the WISSARD Science Team (2019). A Dynamic Holocene Grounding Line: In situ sedimentary evidence from Whillans and Mercer ice streams, West Antarctica. AGU Fall Meeting. San Francisco, CA.
- [15] Campbell, T.D., Patterson, M.O., Skidmore, M.L., Leventer, A., Michaud, A. B., Rosenheim, B.E., Harwood, D., Dore, J.E., Tranter, M., Venturelli, R. A., Priscu, J.C., and the SALSA Science Team (2019). Physical and chemical characterization of sediments from Mercer Subglacial Lake, West Antarctica. AGU Fall Meeting. San Francisco, CA.
- [14] Priscu, J.C., Barker, J.D., Campbell, T., Christner, B.C., Davis, C., Dore, J.E., Fricker, H. A., Gardner, C.B., Harwood, D.M., Leventer, A., Li, W., Lyons, W.B., Michaud, A.B., Patterson, M.O., Rosenheim, B.E., Siegfried, M.R., Skidmore, M.L., Tranter, M., Venturelli, R. A., Vick-Majors, T., Zook, B., and the SALSA Science Team (2019). SALSA: An Integrated Program Focusing on Carbon Transformations in Mercer Subglacial Lake located 1100 m beneath the West Antarctic Ice Sheet, AGU Fall Meeting. San Francisco, CA.
- [13] Venturelli, R. A., Siegfried, M.R., Campbell, T., Fricker, H., Harwood, D., Leventer, A., Michaud, A.B., Patterson, M.O., Rosenheim, B.E., Skidmore, M., and the SALSA Science team (2019). Subglacial Sediments Spanning Scales: A Process-To-Paleo Perspective. 26th Annual WAIS Workshop. Julian, CA.
- [12] Rosenheim, B.E., **Venturelli, R. A.**, Davis, C., Vick-Majors, T, Li, Michaud, A.B., Leventer, A.B., Harwood, D., Christner, B.C., Dore, J.E., Priscu, J.C., and the SALSA Science team (2019). Young Carbon beneath the West Antarctic Ice Sheet: A Unique Carbon Cycle Perspective from Mercer Subglacial Lake. *26th Annual WAIS Workshop*. Julian, CA.
- [11] Campbell, T.D., Patterson, M.O., Skidmore, M.L., Leventer, A., Michaud, A. B., Rosenheim, B.E., Harwood, D., Dore, J.E., Tranter, M., Venturelli, R. A., and the SALSA Science Team (2019). Physical and chemical characterization of sediments from Mercer Subglacial Lake, West Antarctica. 26th Annual WAIS Workshop. Julian, CA.
- [10] Venturelli, R. A., Rosenheim, B. E., Roush, K., Michaud, A., Priscu, J., Skidmore, M., Dore, J., Li, W., Leventer, A., Harwood, D., SALSA Science Team, and the WISSARD Science Team (2019). Subglacial Carbon Pathways Associated with Whillans ad Mercer ice streams: A SALSA and WISSARD sedimentary perspective. XIII International Symposium on Antarctic Earth Sciences. Incheon, Republic of Korea.
- [9] Rosenheim, B.E., Michaud, A., Broda, J., Gagnon, A., Dore, J., Leventer, A., Patterson, M., Campbell, T., Venturelli, R. A., Skidmore, M., Christner, B., Priscu, J.P., and the SALSA Science Team. (2019). Challenges and successes coring sediments from Mercer Subglacial Lake. XIII International Symposium on Antarctic Earth Sciences, Incheon, Republic of Korea.
- [8] Davis, C., Li, W., Vick-Majors, T., Barker, J.D., Michaud, A.B., Dore, J.E., Siegfried, M.R., Tranter, M.S., Gardner, C., Venturelli, R. A., Campbell, T., Patterson, M.O., Leventer A., Harwood, D.M., Rosenheim, B.E., Priscu, J.C., and Christner, B.C. (2019). Life Below an Ice Sheet: Mercer Subglacial Lake, West Antarctica, Astrobiology Science Conference.
- [7] Venturelli, R. A., and Rosenheim, B. (2017). The Absurdity of Certainty: Propagation of Error from Δ_{47} to δ^{18} O Seawater. 6th International Clumped Isotope Workshop. Paris, France.
- [6] Venturelli, R. A., Toth, L.T., and Rosenheim, B. (2017). Hard water, old water-hydrologic cycling in the Florida Keys Reef tract and its effect on interpreting radiocarbon reservoir ages. *Goldschmidt. Paris*, France.
- [5] **Venturelli, R. A.**, and Rosenheim, B. (2015). Understanding pressure baseline through measurements from an Isoprime 5kV mass spectrometer. 5th *International Clumped Isotope Workshop*. St. Petersburg, FL.

- [4] Venturelli, R.A., Rathburn, A E, Burkett, A. M., Paddack, B.D., and Ziebis, W., S. 2014. Epifaunal taxa in an infaunal world. Annual Geological Society of America Meeting. Vancouver, BC Canada. (19–22 October 2014); Geological Society of America Annual Meeting. Program with Abstracts, Vol. 46, No. 6, p.124.
- [3] Venturelli, R.A., Rathburn, A., Paddack, B., Burkett, A., Ziebis, W., and Perez, E. The Ecology of Benthic Foraminifera Living in an Oxygen Minimum Zone on the Eastern Pacific Margin. North Central Geological Society of America Meeting. Lincoln, NE. (24-25 April, 2014); Geological Society of America Programs with Abstracts, Vol. 46, No. 4, p. 64.
- [2] Venturelli, R.A. and Kilibarda, Z.. Heavy Minerals In Beach And Dune Sand Along Southern Lake Michigan. Annual Geological Society of America Meeting. Charlotte, NC. (4-7 November, 2012); Geological Society of America Programs with Abstracts, Vol. 44, No. 7, p. 554.
- [1] Venturelli, R.A., Kilibarda Z., and Graves, N. Geomorphology of Coastal Dunes Near Southern Shores of Lake Michigan. Annual Geological Society of America Meeting. Minneapolis, MN. (9-12 October, 2011); Geological Society of America Programs with Abstracts, Vol. 43, No. 5, p. 251.